Finding Aid for George Robert Swain photographs and papers circa 1870-1947
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Robert Swain photographs and papers circa 1870-1947, 1913-1947
Swain, George Robert, 1866-1947.
1 oversize folders
20 linear feet (in 34 boxes)
University of Michigan staff photographer, 1913-1947 and commercial photographer in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Collection includes some manuscript material but is primarily photographic prints and negatives made by Swain. Photo subjects include university buildings, faculty, and student activities, archeological expeditions to the Near East and, Ann Arbor scenes and landscapes form his travels in the western United States and Canada.
86169 Aa 2; UAm; UAx
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection came from three different sources: Mr. Edwin L. Swain ( 6184 ); the University's Kelsey Museum ( 6687 ); and Mrs. D. W. Hayne ( 2778 ).
The collection is open for research.
George Robert Swain was born on July 15, 1866 in Meredith, New Hampshire. He died at the age of eighty on April 8, 1947, in Ann Arbor, Michigan. An educator and a photographer, his career included thirty-four years of service to the University of Michigan as university photographer from 1913 to 1947.
After irregular primary school education in New Hampshire, Swain traveled to California, where he took and passed the teacher's examination in 1888. He taught first in ungraded country schools and then at a high school in Ventura, California, where one of his students was Edith Louise Rice, who would later become his wife.
Swain received his B.A. degree from the University of Michigan in 1897 and his M.A. degree in 1900. The future Mrs. Swain also spent her last two years of college at Michigan. After receiving the B.A. degree, Swain accepted the position of principal at the Great Falls, Montana High School. Subsequent to the awarding of the M.A. degree, he took another position at a school for boys in Cleveland, Ohio. He did not remain in Cleveland long, however, because as he remarked in a newspaper article, the required dormitory living interfered with his marriage plans.
The Swains settled in Ann Arbor after their marriage in 1900. A few months later, George was offered principalship at the East Side High School in Bay City, Michigan. He served in that capacity for ten years, from 1900-1910. This position led to a similar post at the Lockport Township High School in Lockport, Illinois, where the Swains lived from 1911 to 1912.
In 1913 Swain returned once again to the University of Michigan and began his work on campus with Professor Francis W. Kelsey of the Latin Department. Having previously traveled 2000 miles in 1899 by bicycle through France, Switzerland, Belgium, Holland, and Germany covering Caesar's battlefields with his camera, he was well suited to accompany Professor Kelsey on trips to Europe as a photographic technician. During the four trips they made, Swain photographed valuable manuscripts for the university collection. In addition, immediately after World War I, the two men spent a year traveling throughout Europe on diplomatic passports, offering Swain another opportunity to utilize his photographic talents.
In 1924 and 1925 Swain was part of a university expedition which conducted excavations at Antioch in Pisidia. He and Professor Kelsey drove university cars from Brussels to Naples and three hundred miles across Asia Minor. Their travels also led to a photographic study of the Roman aqueducts. In 1925 and 1926 Swain traveled to Italy, Greece, Mount Athos, and Patmos. He worked with the Franco-American committee in Tunisia and Algeria and was permitted to photograph old manuscripts in eleven monasteries, eight of which were on Mount Athos. On one trip he is reported to have exposed some 1,200 heavy glass plates, all of which were brought back for developing. At one time or another Swain traveled the entire Mediterranean coastline, with the exception of Spain and Morocco.
As university photographer, Swain was allocated an office in the old campus library, where he produced negatives for lantern slides that were used in conjunction with lectures. His work was constantly in demand, and he worked long hours to produce the slides, which were particularly valued by faculties of the fine arts and engineering. Negatives were not developed on campus, however, but in his home darkroom at 1103 Packard Avenue, since the use of chemicals was forbidden in the library building. Examples of George Swain's work can be found in many university, student, and other publications emanating from Ann Arbor during these years.
In addition to commitments as university photographer, George and his wife Edith directed a summer camp for girls, Kamp Kairphree near Alpena, Michigan and later at Lake Charlevoix. Young women from across the country were reported to have attended the camp. Swain also conducted a private photographic business and pursued personal interests with his camera. When the family traveled, he took his camera along and when not traveling, he focused his lens on the campus and surrounding city and countryside. His landscapes, cityscapes, waterscapes, portraits and campus views are a rich historical resource -- all of a remarkable quality -- providing researchers with a unique visual record of the Ann Arbor area in the early twentieth century.
The Swain papers are organized into three series:
Miscellaneous Papers (box 1)
Photographers Log (box 1)
Photographs
Prints (boxes 2-3)
Negatives (boxes 4-33).
Lantern slides (box 34)
The papers and photographs of George R. Swain mainly document Swain's accomplishments as university photographer at the University of Michigan from 1913 to 1947. Researchers should note, however, that this is only a sampling of the photographer's work during these years. The Kelsey Museum of Archaeology at the University of Michigan has an extensive collection of Swain's archaeological negatives and prints, and researchers interested in his full career will want to also look at the Kelsey collection. The Bentley Library material, while including several folders of fine photographs Swain made on his travels with Professor Frances Kelsey, for the most part documents Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan.
The collection at the Bentley Library consists of three series: Miscellaneous Papers; Photographers Log; and Photographs (prints; negatives; and lantern slides. Since the bulk of the collection is comprised of early twentieth century images of Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan, the materials will be of most interest to researchers searching for visual documentation of this part of the state in that time period. There are very few materials beyond the visual, although the lengthy captions attached to many overseas images and the essays, diaries, and letters, are extremely interesting and offer insight into how Swain approached his craft, both as a professional photographer and in his personal work.
Subjects:
Swain, George Robert, 1866-1947.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Archaeology--Egypt.; Archaeology--Middle East.; Archaeology--Turkey.; Au Sable River (Mich.); Photographers.; Swain family.; University of Michigan Near East Research Expedition (1924-1934); University of Michigan--Archaeological expeditions.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dams.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Parks.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Archaeology--Turkey.; Archaeology--Egypt.; Barton Dam (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Camping--Michigan--1891-1900.; Carts and wagons.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Dams--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dexter (Mich.); Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Egypt--Antiquities.; Ferry Field (University of Michigan); Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Island Park (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Laboratories.; Liberty Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Martha Cook building.; Michigan League.; Michigan Union.; Middle East--Antiquities.; Military training.; Nature photography.; Parades and processions--1911-1920.; Parks--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Photographers--Michigan.; Photography of mountains.; Photography of water.; Railroads--Michigan.; Roads--Michigan.; Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Swain, Edith L.; Swain, George Robert, 1866-1947.; Swain family.; Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.; Turkey--Antiquities.; University Hall (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Anniversaries, etc.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan. Class of 1894.; University of Michigan. Class of 1889.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Libraries.; University of Michigan Near East Research Expedition (1924-1934); University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Victory celebrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; War damage.; Winter.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918--War damage.
Contributors:
Swain, Edith L.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Miscellaneous Papers
  The collection begins with several files of Miscellaneous Papers. Although limited in quantity, this is where the researcher must turn for printed documentation on George Swain, since the remainder of materials are wholly photographic. Included are clippings, correspondence, genealogical notes, student writings, diaries, and some photographs. Of special note are several files regarding Swain's association with the Near East Research Center, University of Michigan. These files hold a striking collection of photographs and commentary regarding his travels with Professor Kelsey. Since extensive descriptive writings accompany the photographs, and in order to maintain their contextual association with related manuscript material, they are included as part of this series, rather than in the Photographs: Prints series.
  Nearly all of the expedition images are carefully captioned, some with lengthy, typewritten text. Further context is evident in the numerous letters Swain wrote to his family while on a year-long excursion in 1924 and in a file containing reports, essays and research documents. One report, "Travels of Two Dodge Motors," November 5, 1925, for example, features the vehicles that were donated to the university and driven over "everything from the best of highways to the most abject apologies for roads and even over open country with no roads at all." A series of essays entitled "Notes and Comments of a Wolverine Abroad" describes in vivid language and acute detail several photographic journeys throughout Rome, Italy and Greece. These materials richly illustrate the artistic sensibility, sensitivity, and intelligence Swain brought to his work.
  - "Catalog of Lantern Slides for Educational Institutions," 1902 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Newspaper) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - To Swain, 189?-192? (Box 1)
    - From Swain 1924 (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - George and Edith Swain 1900 (photocopy) (Box 1)
    - Camping Trip on Au Sable 1904-1908 (Box 1)
  - Genealogical Notes (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Near East Research Center, University of Michigan
    - Research and Writings (essays, reports, correspondence) 1925 (Box 1)
    - Expedition Photographs and Commentary
      - Egypt (Box 1)
      - Middle East, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Turkey (Box 1)
    - Post World War I, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Poems circa 1920, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Writings, Student 1896, 1 volumes (Box 1)
- Photographers Log to Set One Negatives
  Swain recorded information about each image in Set One of the negatives in a chronological log. The entry for each negative includes the identifying negative number, the date it was made and a brief note on the subject.
  - Volume 1: 1-1999 (Box 1)
  - Volume 2: 2000-7699 (Box 1)
  - Volume 3: 7700-11,783 (Box 1)
  - Volume 4:11,774-13,344 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Swain photographs (with the exception of the Near East Research prints described in the Miscellaneous Papers series) consist of two sets -- Set One, which has an index and Set Two, a group of images for which an index has not been found. The four- volume index Swain maintained to describe his domestically produced photographs is critical to effective use of the images in Set One, (although more so for the negatives than the prints). There are more than 13,300 items listed in the set. Since many of the negatives do not have related prints, and the housing of plates and film do not describe the image held within, utilizing the index is the most effective way to study the full scope of the materials. It is important, however, to be aware that not all negatives listed are in the collection at the Bentley Library. Only a small portion have actually survived. Apparently Swain destroyed many glass and film negatives after deciding upon the "best" photograph. Others were likely destroyed when no longer needed for some immediate use, and some remain at the Kelsey Museum of Archaeology, University of Michigan. The Bentley Library photographs are arranged in two subseries, Prints and Negatives.
  - Prints
    Included in the photographic Prints, series are two feet of images, most of which are part of Set One, thus corresponding to the four-volume index prepared by Swain, which is in box 1. The Prints subseries is the one most useful to researchers interested in browsing photographs of the Ann Arbor area and the university. Many of the images are fine photographic and photomechanical prints, presumably printed by Swain, but others are black and white copy prints prepared by the Kelsey for reference purposes. Prints can be browsed by subject and for most of them, original negative numbers, which have been extrapolated from the four volume index, are noted on the back of the print.
    The "Ann Arbor and Environs" files includes several dramatic images of the Armistice Day Parade on November 11, 1918; cityscapes and buildings; and pictures of area businesses and residences. There are also a number of lyrical pastoral landscapes, focusing on country roads, waterways, plants and gardens. The "University of Michigan" file is strong in representing campus buildings and campus views, including wintry scenes, all carefully composed. Particularly well documented are the Martha Cook Residence, fraternity and sorority houses, the Michigan League, and the Michigan Union under construction. A third file consists of formal portraits of Ann Arbor and university men, women, children, infants and family groups. Swain also photographed painted portraits and daguerreotypes; images in the folder entitled "Individuals: Copies" include James B. Angell, Professor Walter Dennison, and Martha Cook. The subseries includes two albums containing photographs of engineering projects, physics labs, and scientific apparatus and equipment. Negatives (8x10 film and 1 glass plate) for some of these images and negatives with similar content are filed behind the albums.
    - Personal
      - Swain, George
        - Young Adult (Box 2)
        - Later Years (Box 2)
        - With California Students (Box 2)
        - With Groups (Box 2)
        - With Mrs. Swain (Box 2)
      - Swain, Mrs. (Edith Louise Rice) (Box 2)
      - Swain Family, 2 folders (Box 2)
        (8x10 glass negatives for second folder in box 4; 5x7 negatives for second folder in box 25)
      - Class of 1889 University of Michigan (individual portraits) (Box 2)
      - Homes and Schools (Includes New Hampshire and California) (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor and Environs
      - Activities and Events
        - Armistice Day Parade, Ann Arbor November 11, 1918 (Box 2)
        - Flower Show November 13, 1913 (Box 2)
        - Red Cross Parade, Ann Arbor May 21, 1918 (Box 2)
      - Buildings
        - Businesses (Box 2)
        - Churches (Box 2)
        - Residences
          - Exterior (Box 2)
          - Interior (Box 2)
        - St. Joseph's Hospital (Box 2)
      - Dams (Box 2)
      - Gardens and Plants
        - General (Box 2)
        - Plant Details (Box 2)
        - School War Garden (Box 2)
      - High Schools (University High School, na 12,707) (Box 2)
      - Railroads (Box 2)
      - Views
        - Cedar Bend and Bird Hills Colony (Box 2)
        - Cityscapes (Box 2)
        - Country Roads (Box 2)
        - Landscapes, General (Box 2)
        - Waterscapes (Box 2)
        - Winter Scenes (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan
      - Activities and Events
        - Ferry Field Drills 1917 and Company Exercises, 1918 (Box 2)
        - Student Army Training Corps Exercises, October 1,1918 (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
          (includes "Passing of Old Clock Tower," July 14, 1917)
      - Artworks and Monuments (Photographs of), 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Buildings
        - Alumni House (Box 2)
        - Alumni Memorial Hall (Box 2)
        - Angell Hall (Box 2)
        - Architecture (Box 2)
        - Athletic Facilities (Box 2)
        - Chemistry (Box 2)
        - Dental (Box 2)
        - Engineering (Box 2)
        - Fraternity Houses, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - High Schools (Box 2)
        - Hill Auditorium (Box 2)
        - Lane Hall (Box 2)
        - Law Buildings (Box 2)
        - Libraries (Box 2)
        - Martha Cook Residence, 5 folders (Box 2)
        - Medical Buildings (Box 3)
        - Michigan League Postcards (Box 3)
        - Michigan Union (Box 3)
        - Michigan Union Under Construction, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
        - Museum Building (Box 3)
        - Natural Science (Box 3)
        - Newberry Residence (Box 3)
        - Observatory (Box 3)
        - Pharmacology (Box 3)
        - President's House (Box 3)
        - Science (Includes West Physics) (Box 3)
        - Societies (Box 3)
        - Sorority Houses (Box 3)
        - Tappan Hall (Box 3)
        - University Hall (Box 3)
        - Unnumbered, Unidentified (Box 3)
      - Organizations
        - Bands (Box 3)
        - Class Reunions 1889, 1894, undated (Box 3)
        - Fraternities, Sororities, Societies (Box 3)
          (includes Nu Sigma Nu Fraternity, 1917; Kappa Alpha Theta Sorority,1898; Sinfonia, 1917)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
          (includes Officers of the 1st 700, 1918 Martha Cook groups; 1918 Newberry Hall volunteers;1916 Literary Club; Union kitchen force, 1918)
      - Student Life, 3 prints (Box 3)
        "Going to noon mess at the Union," (2) and students studying)
      - Views
        - General Campus Views (Box 3)
        - Winter Scenes (Box 3)
    - Portraits
      - Families (Box 3)
        (includes Hutchins, Tilley, Peterson, Sunderland, Shirley Smith, Lockwood families)
      - Groups and Pairs (Box 3)
      - Infants and Children (Box 3)
      - Individuals
        - Men (Box 3)
        - Women (Box 3)
        - Copies (from paintings or daguerreotypes) (Box 3)
      - Unnumbered / Unidentified (Box 3)
    - Other
      - Campsites (Box 3)
      - Chicago (Downtown buildings) (Box 3)
      - Michigan (Hubbard, Grayling, Detroit) (Box 3)
      - New York (Pier 14, American Line and ship, State of New York), 2 prints (Box 3)
      - Western United States and Canada (Box 3)
        (negatives in box 25)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (includes tintypes, daguerreotypes, Professor Hoad)
    - Albums
      - Engineering, Physics Laboratories and Mechanical Apparatus, 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - Associated negatives and negatives for similar images, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Negatives
    Negatives form the bulk of the collection (glass plates alone number over six hundred) and include negatives from both Set One and Set Two. Negatives in Set One relate to the photographs described in Swain's four-volume index, a portion of which have corresponding prints in boxes two and three. There is also a supplemental guide at the end of this finding aid, which selectively indexes some of the negatives in Set One that do not have corresponding prints (although there may be some overlap). Many of the negatives without prints or part of the supplemental guide are images of family camping trips, visits to Bay City, Michigan, and family travel throughout the country.
    Researchers should note that in addition to the glass negatives in this set (8x10, 5x8, 5x7, and 4x5), there are nitrate films and safety films, each in both 8x10 and 5x7 formats. Because negatives are stored by format and size, it may be necessary to check in more than one place when retrieving an original by its number.
    There is a subject card file in the reading room which indexes well over 13,000 Swain Set One negatives, although negative size and format is not specified. Researchers should ask the reference staff for assistance with the file, but are reminded that not all of the negatives listed in either the four-volume set or the card file are available. Another resource is the Sam Sturgis collection. A selection of Set One Swain negatives were printed by Sturgis, Ann Arbor photographer, including images of university buildings, such as the Observatory, Botanical Gardens, Architecture Building, Law Buildings and Ann Arbor area residences and churches. See the Sturgis finding aid for location of the photographs.
    Set Two of the Negatives Series is comprised of nine small boxes of 5x8, 5x7 and 4x5 inch glass plates. The negatives came to the library from the Kelsey Museum without an index (according to the Kelsey, an index has not yet been found). Most of the images are majestic landscapes of western United States and Canada, Swain family portraits, and family travel.
    - Set One
      - 8x10 Glass Negatives
        - Unnumbered (Box 4)
          (mainly family portraits--prints in box 2: Swain Family. Also Bird's Eye View Union Tower, Old Campus Fence and Snow, Homeopathic Hospital, 1903, Pres. Harry Hutchins)
        - 94-2624 (Box 5)
        - 2632-2983 (Box 6)
        - 3001-3299 (Box 7)
        - 3300-3808 (Box 8)
        - 3814-4180 (Box 9)
        - 4719-4685 (Box 10)
        - 4864-5136 (Box 11)
        - 5181-5279 (Box 12)
        - 5300-5939 (Box 13)
        - 5940-12,687 (Box 14)
      - 8x10 Film Negatives
        - 8942-13,202B (Box 14)
      - 5x7 Glass Negatives (Box 15)
        - 1212-1668 (Box 15)
        - 1669-1768 (Box 16)
        - 1769-1875 (Box 17)
        - 1876-1971 (Box 18)
        - 1972-2058 (Box 19)
        - 2060-2274 (Box 20)
        - 2275-2818 (Box 21)
        - 2819-11,933 (Box 22)
      - 4x5 Glass Negatives
        - 11,727; 12,670; 12,776; 12,821; 12,902 (Box 22)
      - 4x5, 5x7 Nitrate Negatives
        - 2071, 2076, 2077, 2105, 2117, 2120, 2121, 2124, 2128, 2129 2131, 2132, 2133, 2136, 2288, 2290, 2292, 2411, 2424, 2459, 2472, 2480, 2498, 2499, 2500-2511, 2516, 11,649; 11,667; 11,674; 11,676; 11,697;13,097 (Box 22)
      - 5x7 Film Negatives (Box 23)
        - Unnumbered (James W. Angell, Joseph B. Davis, Henry S. Frieze, C.S. Denison) (Box 23)
        - 11,514-13,324 (Box 23)
    - Set Two
      (Mainly landscapes of Western Canada and the United States; some portraits of children and family)
      - 5x8 Glass Negatives
        - 40-679 (Box 24)
        - 710-1731 (Box 25)
        - Unnumbered (Box 25)